Hey guys, in this video, we will be
starting
off with our first ever unit in physics,
and
that is kinematics. So, first of all, what
is
kinematics? Kinematics belongs to the
stream
of physics of mechanics, which deals with
the
motion of objects. For example, once we
learn
kinematics, we'll be able to calculate a
lot
of different motion, we'll learn the
difference
between velocity, acceleration, and
displacement
or position, and we'll be able to
calculate
a lot of these questions. Let's first
start
by reviewing velocity, displacement, and
acceleration.
So, I'll be introducing velocity and
acceleration,
and based on what we've learned in the
past,
displacement, we know, is the change in
position,
delta-x, which is equal to the final
position
minus the initial position.
And keep in mind, in physics, when we use
this
triangle, it represents delta, which means
change
in, change in.
So, in this case, it would be change in x
or
position. Now, since displacement is a
vector,
it only accounts for the initial position
and
the final position, it does not matter
what
path you take. And that is the same thing
for
velocity. Velocity.
Now, velocity is the displacement over a
period
of time, sorry, the displacement over a
of time. And delta-t means change in time.
Now, since we know that velocity is a
vector,
that means that it has to have a position
as
well, sorry, a direction as well. And
since
we're dealing with 1D kinematics, usually
it's
going to be on one dimension.
And let's say we have a cart, and this
cart
moves to the right. Well then, right will
be
the direction. For example, its velocity
was
4 metres per second.
If the magnitude of the velocity was 4
metres
per second, then the velocity would be
depicted
as v equals 4 metres per second, right.
So make sure that for all of these, you
have
to include a direction. Vectors always
must
have a direction. Unless a question asks
you
for the magnitude of the velocity or
whatever
you're calculating, you must always state
up,
down, right, north, and so on.
Another way of depicting direction is
positive
or negative. And this usually is used only
in
1D kinematics, not in 2D or 3D.
And this means that we're going to treat
right
as a positive side and left as a negative
side.
So let's say if we have this cart going
this
way now at a speed of 3 metres per second,
then
the new velocity, v new, would be equal
to,
well, we're using sine as a direction, so
it
would be negative 3 metres per second.
So usually right is positive and left is
negative,
up is also positive, and down is negative.
Now, onto our next value.
We're going to have acceleration. So, you
might
have heard of acceleration before, but
you've
probably never actually known the formula
for
this. You've probably known velocity, it's
metres
per second. But acceleration is just
delta-v
over delta-t. It's just how much velocity
changes
over time. So basically it's the same
thing
as delta-x over delta-t squared, if you
sub
it in. And these both work.
It's basically the slope of the velocity,
how
much the velocity changes over time.
So, if you think about it, if acceleration
is
zero, then there still can be velocity.
But if acceleration is positive, velocity
is
going to go up, and if acceleration is
negative,
it's going to go down. So, now keep in
mind
that acceleration also has a vector.
And let's say that we have a question for
this
cart, or we have a question for this cart
right
now. And at x equals 1, the cart starts
off,
so we're going to have a cart. And
at x equals 5, the cart is at position x
equals 5, and it takes, let's say, 10
seconds
for this cart to go from here to there.
And you want to calculate the velocity.
Well, let's first establish our
directions.
If it's going from here to there, then
it's
going in the positive direction. This is
the
positive direction, this is the negative
direction,
so the velocity will be positive.
We know that velocity is delta-x over
delta
t, change in position over change in time.
So we can write that delta-x over delta-t.
We know that delta-t is 10. delta-x is the
final
x position, 5 minus the initial.
Delta is always final minus initial. And
you
would get 2 over 5 metres per second,
don't
forget the positive as well. And that
would
be the basics of how we calculate 1D
kinematics.
So, now that's basically all for the
introduction
of kinematics. We've learned about
displacement,
acceleration, and velocity. And these are
basically
the main things that we're going to be
dealing
with in kinematics. There's really nothing
other
than this in this unit itself that you're
going
to have to know. And after we get into 2D
kinematics,
which you'll find pretty similar, we're
going
to be going over the formulae that we can
use
to calculate a lot of these questions. But
that's
it for this video, I hope you enjoyed, and
we'll
see you in the next one. Bye!